{
  "topic": "Evolution of Education and Press",
  "subtopic": "Newspapers and Journals (1780-1936)",
  "flashcards": [
    {
      "id": "fc001",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bengal Gazette / Original Calcutta General Advertiser (1780)?",
      "back": "Founder: James Augustus Hickey. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal, Bihar, Orissa. First newspaper published in India in English. Known for independent journalism and outspoken criticism of British East India Company"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc002",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Madras Courier (1784/85)?",
      "back": "Founder: Richard Johnston. Place: Madras. First newspaper to be published from Madras"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc003",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Herald (1789)?",
      "back": "Place: Bombay. First newspaper to be published from Bombay. In English, came with title Indian Herald"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc004",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bengal Gazette (1818)?",
      "back": "Founder: Harish Chandra Ray. Place: Calcutta. First Bengali newspaper"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc005",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Sambad Kaumudi (1821)?",
      "back": "Founder: Raja Ram Mohan Roy. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. Bengali weekly newspaper that promoted social and religious reform"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc006",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Mirat-ul-Akbar (1822)?",
      "back": "Founder: Raja Ram Mohan Roy. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. First Persian language journal that discussed current events and social issues"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc007",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Jam-i-Jahan Numah (1822)?",
      "back": "Place: Calcutta. First Urdu language paper. Was run by an English Firm"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc008",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Banga-Duta (1822)?",
      "back": "Founder: Raja Ram Mohan Roy and Dwarkanath Tagore. Place: Calcutta. Weekly published in 4 different languages: English, Bengali, Persian and Hindi"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc009",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bombay Samachar (1822)?",
      "back": "Founder: Fardunjee Marzban. Place: Bombay. First newspaper in Gujarati"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc010",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bangadarshan (1873)?",
      "back": "Founder: Bankim Chandra Chatterji. Place: Calcutta. In Bengali Language"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc011",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bombay Times (1838)?",
      "back": "Founder: Thomas Bennett. Place: Bombay. Later from 1861 came to be known as Times of India, published till date. Founded by Robert Knight but actual publication started by Thomas Bennett"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc012",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Hindu Patriot (1853)?",
      "back": "Founder: Girishchandra Ghosh. Place: Calcutta. Later Harishchandra Mukherji became owner-cum-editor"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc013",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Rast Goftar (1851)?",
      "back": "Founder: Dadabhai Naoroji. Place: Bombay. Spread: Bombay, Gujarat, Sindh. Gujarati fortnightly newspaper advocated for Indian economic and political rights. Naoroji used it to educate Indians about their rights and mobilise them against British rule"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc014",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Voice of India (1883)?",
      "back": "Founder: Dadabhai Naoroji. Place: Bombay. Later incorporated into the Indian Spectator"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc015",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Som Prakash (1858)?",
      "back": "Founder: Dwarkanath VidyaBhushan. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. Bengali weekly newspaper promoted social, political and educational reforms. Used to advocate for women's rights, education, and widow remarriage"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc016",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Indian Mirror (1862)?",
      "back": "Founder: Devendra Nath Tagore and Man Mohan Ghosh. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. English fortnightly newspaper"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc017",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Bengalee (1862)?",
      "back": "Started by Girish Chandra Ghosh and later taken over by Surendranath Banerjee. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc018",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Pioneer (1865)?",
      "back": "Founder: George Allen. Place: Allahabad. Spread: United Provinces"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc019",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Amrita Bazar Patrika (1868)?",
      "back": "Founder: Sisir Kumar ghosh and Motilal Ghosh. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. Bengali in beginning, later became English. Leading voice for bengali middle class"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc020",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Tahzib-ul-Akhlaq (1871)?",
      "back": "Founder: Sir Syed Ahmed Khan. Place: Aligarh. Spread: North India. Urdu language journal advocating for women's education, reform in Muslim family law, modernization of Muslim society"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc021",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Indian Statesman (1875)?",
      "back": "Founder: Robert Knight. Place: Calcutta. Later renamed as The Statesman"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc022",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Hindu (1878)?",
      "back": "Founder: G.S. Iyer, Vir Raghavacharya and Subba Rao Pandit. Place: Madras. Spread: Madras and Mysore. Initially weekly newspaper, known for moderate political view"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc023",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Swadeshnamitran (1882)?",
      "back": "Founder: G. Subramaniya Iyer. Place: Madras. One of the earliest Tamil newspapers and the longest in print"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc024",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Advocate (1878)?",
      "back": "Founder: G.P. Verma. Place: Lucknow. Spread: United Provinces"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc025",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Kesari (1881)?",
      "back": "Founder: Bal Gangadhar Tilak. Place: Poona. Spread: Bombay and Central India. Marathi language newspaper advocated for Indian self-rule. Mahratta (1881): An English weekly"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc026",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Tribune (1881)?",
      "back": "Founder: Dayal Singh Majeetha. Place: Lahore. Spread: Punjab and North India. Daily newspaper"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc027",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Arya Gazette (1882)?",
      "back": "Founder: Pandit Dayanand Saraswati. Place: Lahore. Spread: Punjab and North India. Published in both English and Hindi"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc028",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Akhbar-i-Am (1886)?",
      "back": "Founder: Maulavi Zakaullah. Place: Lahore. Spread: Punjab and North India"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc029",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Gaujrat and the Gujratis (1882)?",
      "back": "Founder: Behramji Malabari. Place: Bombay. Spread: Bombay and Gujarat"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc030",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Sudharak (1888)?",
      "back": "Founder: Gopal Krishna Agarkar. Place: Poona. Spread: Bombay and Central India. Marathi language newspaper promoted social reform"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc031",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Hitavada (1911)?",
      "back": "Founder: GK Gokhale. Place: Nagpur. Spread: central India. Published in both English and Marathi. Advocated for social reform and economic development"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc032",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Indu Prakash (1888)?",
      "back": "Founder: Gopalhari Deshmukh. Place: Poona. Spread: Bombay and Central India"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc033",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Leader (1907)?",
      "back": "Founder: Madan Mohan Malviya. Place: Allahabad. Spread: United Provinces"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc034",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Prabuddha Bharat (1896)?",
      "back": "Founder: P. Aiyasami, B. R. Rajam Iyer, G. G. Narasimhacharya, B. V. Kamesvara Iyer at behest of Swami Vivekananda. Place: Calcutta. Spread: India and the world. English language monthly journal promoted Hindu philosophy and culture"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc035",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Udbodhana (1899)?",
      "back": "Founder: Swami Vivekananda. Place: Calcutta. Spread: India and the world"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc036",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Indian Opinion (1903)?",
      "back": "Founder: M.K Gandhi. Place: Durban, South Africa. Spread: South Africa and India. Weekly newspaper advocated for rights of Indian immigrants"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc037",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Young India (1919)?",
      "back": "Founder: M.K Gandhi. Place: Ahmedabad. Spread: Bombay Presidency. Weekly journal promoted Gandhi's philosophy of non-violence and civil disobedience"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc038",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Nav Jeevan (1929)?",
      "back": "Founder: M.K Gandhi. Place: Ahmedabad. Spread: Bombay. Gujarati language weekly promoted social reforms and Gandhi's philosophy"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc039",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Harijan (1932)?",
      "back": "Founder: M.K Gandhi. Place: Ahmedabad. Spread: Bombay. English and Hindi weekly journal advocated for rights of Dalits"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc040",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Sandhya (1906)?",
      "back": "Founder: Brahmabandhab Upadhyay. Place: Bengal"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc041",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Yugantar (1906)?",
      "back": "Founder: Barindra Kumar Ghosh and Bhupendra Dutta. Place: Bengal. Political weekly served as propaganda organ for revolutionary organisation Anushilan Samiti"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc042",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Karmayogi (1909)?",
      "back": "Founder: Aurobindo Ghosh. Place: Puducherry. Spread: India and the world. Published in English"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc043",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Kudi Arasu (1910)?",
      "back": "Founder: E.V. Ramaswamy Naicker (Periyar). In Tamil language"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc044",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Comrade (1911)?",
      "back": "Founder: Maulana Mohammad Ali. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. English language weekly advocated for Indian self-rule and Muslim rights"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc045",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Al-Balagh (1912)?",
      "back": "Founder: Abul Kalam Azad. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. Urdu weekly supported Indian self-rule and Muslim rights"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc046",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Azad (1912)?",
      "back": "Founder: Abul Kalam Azad. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. Published in Urdu"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc047",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Al-Hilal (1912)?",
      "back": "Founder: Abul Kalam Azad. Place: Calcutta. Spread: Bengal and Bihar. Urdu weekly newspaper promoted Islamic thoughts and culture"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc048",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bombay Chronicle (1913)?",
      "back": "Started by Firoze Shah Mehta and edited by B. G. Horniman. Place: Bombay. Spread: Bombay and Gujarat. Daily newspaper"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc049",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "New India (1914)?",
      "back": "Founder: Annie Besant. Place: Madras. Spread: Madras and Mysore"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc050",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Independent (1919)?",
      "back": "Founder: Motilal Nehru. Place: Allahabad. Spread: United Provinces"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc051",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Hindustan Times (1920)?",
      "back": "Founder: Sunder Singh Lyallpuri Later edited by K M Panikkar. Place: Delhi. Spread: All India. English language daily newspaper, used as part of the Akali Dal Movement"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc052",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Mook Nayak (1920)?",
      "back": "Founder: B.R Ambedkar. Place: Bombay. Spread: Bombay. Marathi language weekly advocated for rights of Dalits"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc053",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bahishkrit Bharat (1927)?",
      "back": "Founder: B.R. Ambedkar. Marathi fortnightly"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc054",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "The Swarajya (1921)?",
      "back": "Founder: C. Rajagopalachari. Place: Madras. Spread: Madras and Mysore. Published in English"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc055",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Free Hindustan (1936)?",
      "back": "Founder: Tarak Nath Das. Place: Canada and USA. Spread in India and the world. English language journal advocated for self-rule and international cooperation"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc056",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Hindustan Dainik (1936)?",
      "back": "Founder: Madan Mohan Malaviya. Place: Lucknow. Spread: United Provinces. Hindi language daily newspaper advocated for Hindu nationalism"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc057",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bandi Jivan?",
      "back": "Founder: Sachindranath Sanyal. Place: Bengal"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc058",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "National Herald (1938)?",
      "back": "Founder: Jawaharlal Nehru. Place: Established in Lucknow. Details: Founded as a tool to win independence. Banned by British government in 1942 during Quit India movement till 1945"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc059",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Indian Sociologist?",
      "back": "Founder: Shyamji Krishnavarma. Place of Publication: London"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc060",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Bande Mataram?",
      "back": "Founder: Madam Bikaji Cama. Place of Publication: Paris"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc061",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Talvar?",
      "back": "Founder: Virendranath Chattopadhyaya. Place of Publication: Berlin"
    },
    {
      "id": "fc062",
      "category": "Newspapers and Journals",
      "front": "Ghadar?",
      "back": "Founder: Lala Hardayal. Place of Publication: San Francisco. Details: The Ghadar Party put out this weekly, meaning revolt, using a small hand press. It first came out in Urdu, then Gurumukhi. Later it was also published in Gujarati, Hindi, English, German etc"
    }
  ],
  "quizzes": {
    "mcq": [
      {
        "id": "mcq001",
        "question": "First newspaper published in India in English (1780)?",
        "options": [
          "Madras Courier",
          "Bengal Gazette (Hickey)",
          "Herald",
          "Bombay Times"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Bengal Gazette/Original Calcutta General Advertiser (1780) by James Augustus Hickey was first newspaper in India in English."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq002",
        "question": "First Bengali newspaper (1818)?",
        "options": [
          "Sambad Kaumudi",
          "Bengal Gazette (Harish Chandra Ray)",
          "Bangadarshan",
          "Som Prakash"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Bengal Gazette (1818) by Harish Chandra Ray was first Bengali newspaper."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq003",
        "question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy founded which newspapers?",
        "options": [
          "Only Sambad Kaumudi",
          "Sambad Kaumudi (1821), Mirat-ul-Akbar (1822), Banga-Duta (1822)",
          "Only Mirat-ul-Akbar",
          "Only Banga-Duta"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy founded Sambad Kaumudi (1821 Bengali), Mirat-ul-Akbar (1822 Persian), and Banga-Duta (1822 with Dwarkanath Tagore, 4 languages)."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq004",
        "question": "First Urdu language paper (1822)?",
        "options": [
          "Mirat-ul-Akbar",
          "Jam-i-Jahan Numah",
          "Tahzib-ul-Akhlaq",
          "Al-Hilal"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Jam-i-Jahan Numah (1822) was first Urdu language paper, run by an English Firm."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq005",
        "question": "First Gujarati newspaper (1822)?",
        "options": [
          "Rast Goftar",
          "Bombay Samachar (Fardunjee Marzban)",
          "Gaujrat and the Gujratis",
          "Bombay Times"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Bombay Samachar (1822) by Fardunjee Marzban was first newspaper in Gujarati."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq006",
        "question": "Bombay Times (1838) later became?",
        "options": [
          "Indian Express",
          "Times of India (from 1861)",
          "Hindustan Times",
          "Indian Statesman"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Bombay Times (1838) by Thomas Bennett later from 1861 came to be known as Times of India, published till date."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq007",
        "question": "Dadabhai Naoroji founded which newspapers?",
        "options": [
          "Only Rast Goftar",
          "Rast Goftar (1851) and Voice of India (1883)",
          "Only Voice of India",
          "The Bengalee"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Dadabhai Naoroji founded Rast Goftar (1851, Gujarati) and Voice of India (1883, later incorporated into Indian Spectator)."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq008",
        "question": "Kesari (1881) and Mahratta (1881) founded by?",
        "options": [
          "Gopal Krishna Agarkar",
          "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
          "G.K. Gokhale",
          "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Kesari (Marathi) and Mahratta (English weekly) both founded in 1881 by Bal Gangadhar Tilak, advocated for Indian self-rule."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq009",
        "question": "M.K. Gandhi founded how many newspapers?",
        "options": [
          "One",
          "Two",
          "Four (Indian Opinion 1903, Young India 1919, Nav Jeevan 1929, Harijan 1932)",
          "Three"
        ],
        "correct": 2,
        "explanation": "Gandhi founded Indian Opinion (1903 Durban), Young India (1919 Ahmedabad), Nav Jeevan (1929 Gujarati), Harijan (1932 for Dalits)."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq010",
        "question": "Abul Kalam Azad founded which newspapers?",
        "options": [
          "Only Al-Hilal",
          "Al-Balagh (1912), The Azad (1912), and Al-Hilal (1912)",
          "Only Al-Balagh",
          "Only The Azad"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Abul Kalam Azad founded Al-Balagh (1912), The Azad (1912), and Al-Hilal (1912), all Urdu newspapers supporting Indian self-rule and Muslim rights."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq011",
        "question": "B.R. Ambedkar founded which newspapers for Dalits?",
        "options": [
          "Only Mook Nayak",
          "Mook Nayak (1920) and Bahishkrit Bharat (1927)",
          "Only Bahishkrit Bharat",
          "Harijan"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "B.R. Ambedkar founded Mook Nayak (1920, Marathi weekly) and Bahishkrit Bharat (1927, Marathi fortnightly) advocating for rights of Dalits."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq012",
        "question": "Yugantar (1906) served as propaganda organ for?",
        "options": [
          "Congress",
          "Revolutionary organisation Anushilan Samiti",
          "Muslim League",
          "Arya Samaj"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Yugantar (1906) by Barindra Kumar Ghosh and Bhupendra Dutta served as propaganda organ for revolutionary organisation Anushilan Samiti."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq013",
        "question": "National Herald (1938) founded by?",
        "options": [
          "Mahatma Gandhi",
          "Jawaharlal Nehru",
          "Motilal Nehru",
          "Subhas Bose"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "National Herald (1938) founded by Jawaharlal Nehru in Lucknow as tool to win independence, banned 1942 during Quit India."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq014",
        "question": "Indian Sociologist published from?",
        "options": [
          "Calcutta",
          "London",
          "Paris",
          "Berlin"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Indian Sociologist by Shyamji Krishnavarma published from London."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq015",
        "question": "Bande Mataram founded by Madam Bikaji Cama published from?",
        "options": [
          "London",
          "Paris",
          "Berlin",
          "San Francisco"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Bande Mataram founded by Madam Bikaji Cama published from Paris."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq016",
        "question": "Talvar founded by Virendranath Chattopadhyaya published from?",
        "options": [
          "London",
          "Paris",
          "Berlin",
          "San Francisco"
        ],
        "correct": 2,
        "explanation": "Talvar founded by Virendranath Chattopadhyaya published from Berlin."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq017",
        "question": "Ghadar (meaning revolt) founded by?",
        "options": [
          "Shyamji Krishnavarma",
          "Madam Bikaji Cama",
          "Lala Hardayal",
          "Virendranath Chattopadhyaya"
        ],
        "correct": 2,
        "explanation": "Ghadar founded by Lala Hardayal, published from San Francisco by Ghadar Party."
      },
      {
        "id": "mcq018",
        "question": "Ghadar initially came out in which languages?",
        "options": [
          "Only Urdu",
          "Urdu, then Gurumukhi, later Gujarati, Hindi, English, German etc",
          "Only English",
          "Only Punjabi"
        ],
        "correct": 1,
        "explanation": "Ghadar first came out in Urdu, then Gurumukhi, later also published in Gujarati, Hindi, English, German etc."
      }
    ],
    "comprehensive": []
  }
}